James W. Wall Photograph Collection 1993.0062
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
James W. Wall Photograph Collection
undated, 1934-1991
1993.0062
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
1.25 Linear feet
Photographs of locomotives and scenes of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, the Boston & Albany Railroad and the Boston & Maine Railroad, and of street railroads in the Boston, Massachusetts, area, most taken in the 1930s and 1940s, most likely by James W. Wall. The collection also includes photographs of scenes that show men in the United States Army in World War II in Europe and after the war in Japan.
Wall, James W.
Biography
Little is known about James W. Wall other than he served in the United States Army during and after World War II, stationed throughout Europe, including London, England, Normandy, Paris, and Reims, France. He was briefly stationed in Japan following the war. Evidence from the postcards in the collection show that he lived in Arlington, Virginia, in the 1970s and 1980s and was at that time a retired Major.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 914 black and white photographic prints of railroad locomotives and trains and street railroads, most of them in the Boston, Massachusetts, area, as well as images of airplanes, automobiles, and ships, from unknown locations, all dated from 1934 to 1941 and then from 1945 to the early 1950s and then again in the 1970s and 1980s. The trains and engines photographed are predominantly those of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, the Boston & Maine Railroad, and the Boston & Albany Railroad, with a few from other railroad lines. The collection also includes photographs of men in the United States Army during World War II in locations in Europe (particularly France and England), and after the war in Japan.
It is likely that James W. Wall was the photographer for the images but that cannot be confirmed by the images themselves. The only information available on each photograph is the date -- year, month, and day -- it was taken. Location information is not available. The railroad photographs have been sorted into order by railroads but that was done only when the railroad could be distinguished from the image itself. One particular man's image is scattered throughout all the photographs and it is presumed that he is Mr. Wall.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Paul Dickson of Garrett Park, Maryland, in 1993.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the railroads of New England, particularly the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Boston and Albany Railroad.; Boston and Maine Railroad.; Locomotives--Photographs.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Photographic prints.; Postcards.; Railroads--Photographs.; Street-railroads.; Trolleys--Photographs.; World War, 1939-1945--Photographs.
- Series I: Collection, undated, 1934-1991
  - Railroad, undated, 1934-1991
    - Bangor & Aroostook Railroad, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boston & Albany Railroad, 1934-1940, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boston & Maine Railroad, 1934-1939, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Edaville Railroad, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Maine Central Railroad, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - New York Central Railroad, 1937, 1940, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1934-1941, 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    - Penn Central, 1973, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, 1940, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rio Grande Railroad, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rutland Railroad, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Southern Pacific Railroad, 1939, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Union Freight Railroad, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified, 1934-1989
      - 1934-1941, 1944-1947, 1950, 1952 (Box 4)
      - 1976-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Scope and Content Note
        Subjects include Amtrak and the American Freedom Train.
    - Street railroads, most in the Boston, Massachusetts, area, 1934-1953, 1972-1989 (Box 5)
    - Postcards addressed to James W. Wall, with railroad and trolley scenes, undated, 1971-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Model trains, 1936, 1974-1980, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Other Transportation, 1934-1988
    - Ships and boats, 1934-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Automobiles and buses, 1934-1936, 1977, 1984, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Airplanes and airports (includes airplanes at the National Air & Space Museum in Washington, D.C.), 1936, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Military, undated, 1941-1952
    - undated, 1941-1945, 1948-1952 (Box 6)
      Photographs from 1941-1945 were taken at locations in France and England; photographs from 1948-1952 show locations in Japan.
    - 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General, not of other categories, 1936, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)